Gabriel Mateo Mejía Sepúlveda

BIOMEDICAL & ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING · UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

□ (+57) 3213591911 | ☑ qm.mejia@uniandes.edu.co | ★ q27182818.qithub.io/ | ☑ q27182818 | 匝 Gabriel-Mateo-Mejia | ☎ Gabriel Mejía

Profile_

Last year master's student in biomedical engineering focused on deep learning for biomedical applications, founded by a Google DeepMind scholarship. My interests are at the intersection of Al/ML, omics data, and drug discovery. I am particularly excited about applications such as inverse protein folding, small molecule design, digital twins, early diagnosis techniques, and the recognition of therapeutic targets in cancer/aging. I have extensive experience in Al for transcriptomic analysis and current computer vision techniques. I consider myself oriented to problem solving and I highly value the translation of theoretical studies to real-world clinical practice.

Education

M. S. Biomedical Engineering

Bogotá, Colombia

Jan. 2022 - Dec. 2023

Universidad de los Andes

- Google DeepMind scholar.
- Emphasis in Deep Learning applied to transcriptomic analysis.
- Relevant courses: Advanced Machine Learning, Computer Vision.

B. E. Biomedical Engineering - Summa Cum Laude

Universidad de los Andes, GPA: 4.80/5.0

Relevant courses: Processing and Analysis of Biomedical Images, Biotechnology and Biomolecular Engineering.

B. E. Electronic Engineering - Summa Cum Laude

Bogotá, Colombi

Bogotá, Colombia

Jan. 2018 - Apr. 2022

Universidad de los Andes. GPA: 4.81/5.0

• Relevant courses: Dynamic Systems, Reinforcement Learning, Stochastic Processes.

• Minor in chinese language & culture

Aug. 2017 - Oct. 2022

Research Experience

Biomedical Computer Vision Group

Bogotá Colombia

RESEARCH PROJECTS PROFESSIONAL

Jun. 2021 - Present

- · Principal investigator: Pablo Arbelaez Ph.D.
- Developed methods for gene expression prediction from histology images in spatial transcriptomics using graph neural networks (GNNs).
- Used logistic models to develop a state-of-the-art classification/detection model for cancer diagnosis using bulk RNA-seq.
- · Designed a random forest model for 3D brain tumor segmentation in multi-parametric magnetic resonance imaging scans.
- Developing interpretable transcriptomic aging clocks using GNNs.

Research Group in Nano-Biomaterials, Cellular Engineering and Bio-Printing

Bogotá, Colombia

WET LAB RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2020 - Jun 2021

- Principal investigator: Juan Carlos Cruz Ph.D.
- Worked on the development of a library of anti-microbial and translocating peptides assessed by yeast surface display methods.

Selected Publications

SEPAL: Spatial Gene Expression Prediction from Local Graphs

ICCV CVAMD2023

Mejía, G. M., Cardenas, P., Ruiz, D., Castillo, A., Arbeláez, P.

Oct. 2023

https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2309.01036

CanDLE: Illuminating Biases in Transcriptomic Pan-Cancer Diagnosis

MICCAI CMMCA2022

Mejía, G. M., Bloch, N., Arbeláez, P.

Sept. 2022

Hirni: Segmentation of Brain Tumors in Multi-parametric Magnetic Resonance Imaging Scans

CI-BI&BI

MEJÍA, G. M., MORENO, D., RUIZ, D., APARICIO, N.

https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-17266-3_7

Dec. 2021

https://doi.org/10.1109/CI-IBBI54220.2021.9626115

Teaching Experience

OCTOBER 21, 2023 GABRIEL MEJIA · RÉSUMÉ

Universidad de los Andes.

Jul. 2017 - Dec. 2021

• Teaching assistant of the following undergraduate courses: Dynamic systems (2 years), undergraduate physics support (1.5 years), undergraduate mathematics support (1.5 years), Freshman students' Support Program (1 year), digital systems (1 semester), control systems analysis (1 semester), biomedical image processing and analysis (1 semester), electronics workshop (1 semester).

Honors & Awards

2023	Best Paper Award, ICCV Workshop on Computer Vision for Automated Medical Diagnosis	CDG, France
2022	Best Paper Award, MICCAI Workshop on Computational Mathematics Modeling in Cancer Analysis.	SIN, Singapur
2022	DeepMind Scholarship , One of three awarded by academic excellence and research in Artificial Intelligence.	BOG, Colombic
2022	Otto de Greiff Contest, Third best undergraduate thesis in Colombia (Appropriated technologies category).	CLO, Colombia
2022	Best Graduation GPA, Of the electronic and biomedical engineering departments.	BOG, Colombic
2022	Summa Cum Laude , Top 1% graduation GPA in engineering faculty over the past 5 years and integral merits.	BOG, Colombia
2019	Ramon de Zubiría, Highest overall GPA of biomedical and electronic engineering departments.	BOG, Colombic

Skills_

Programming Languages Python, Matlab, R, C/C++.

Scientific Software NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, RDKit, Scanpy, Squidpy.

ML Frameworks Pytorch, Scikit-Learn, H2O. **ML Monitoring** Weights and biases.

Languages Spanish (Native), English (Professional), German (Basic).

Events

2023	Oral Presentation , ICCV workshop on Computer Vision for Automated Medical Diagnostics	CDG, France
2023	Poster Presentation, 10th Aging Research and Drug Discovery Conference	CPH, Denmark
2023	Poster Presentation, Khipu: 4th Latin American Meeting In Artificial Intelligence	MVD, Uruguay
2022	Speaker, IEEE R9 Latin American Student Congress	BOG, Colombia
2022	Oral Presentation , MICCAI workshop on Computational Mathematics Modeling in Cancer Analysis	SIN, Singapur
2021	Oral Presentation , IEEE 2nd International Congress of Biomedical Engineering and Bioengineering	BOG, Colombia